Register of the Ephraim Douglass Adams papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Ephraim Douglass Adams papers
1908-1929
XX104
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box (0.4 linear feet)
Correspondence and leaflets relating to the administration and finances of Stanford University and to American participation in World War I. Correspondence mostly with Herbert Hoover. Includes a series of leaflets by E. D. Adams, entitled Why We Are at War with Germany, 1918. Includes photocopied correspondence.
Adams, Ephraim Douglass, 1865-1930.
Access
Collection is open for research.
Access to audiovisual materials requires at least two weeks advance notice. Audiovisual materials include sound recordings, video recordings, and motion picture film. Hoover staff will determine whether use copies of the materials requested can be made available. Some materials may not be accessible even with advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Location of Originals
Original correspondence in: Stanford University Archives.
Biographical/Historical Note
American historian; director of the Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace, 1919-1925.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Ephraim Douglass Adams Papers consist of correspondence and speeches and writings. The correspondence includes his exchanges of letters with Herbert Hoover regarding the finances and other operations of Stanford University. The letters also concern The Commission for Relief in Belgium and the establishment of the Hoover Library at Stanford University. The correspondence series also includes a lengthy letter to Ray Lyman Wilbur in which Adams sets forth his views on the administration of Stanford University and the role of the faculty in the university. The speeches and writings series includes copies of a multi-part pamphlet entitled Why We are At War with Germany in which Adams explains his view of why America had to go to war with Germany in World War I. The speeches and writings series also contains a lengthy speech in which Adams gives his personal reminiscences of Herbert Hoover as an individual and as an administrator.
Arrangement Statement
The collection is arranged into 2 series: Correspondence and Speeches and writings
Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Stanford University.; World War, 1914-1918--United States.
- Correspondence, 1908-1927
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1908-1925
    - 1908-1910 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    - 1911-1912 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - 1913-1914 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - 1915 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - 1917-1918 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - 1921-1925 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Hoover, Lou Henry, 1917-1921 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Lutz, Ralph H., 1923-1927 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Wilbur, Ray Lyman, 1915 (Box-folder 1: 9)
- Speeches and writings, 1918-1929
  - Why We Are at War with Germany, parts I - X, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - "Snap Shots of Herbert Hoover", 1929 (Box-folder 1: 11)